<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The araignment of Iohn Selman, who was executed neere Charing-Crosse the 7. of Ianuary, 1612. for a fellony by him committed in the Kings Chappell at White-Hall vpon Christmas day last, in presence of the King and diuers of the nobility</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11884</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22183</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117088</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852303</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852303</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17619</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11884)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17619)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1610:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The araignment of Iohn Selman, who was executed neere Charing-Crosse the 7. of Ianuary, 1612. for a fellony by him committed in the Kings Chappell at White-Hall vpon Christmas day last, in presence of the King and diuers of the nobility</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 17, [3] p. : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. H[all] for Thomas Archer, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head Pallace,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition dated 1611.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Selman, John, d. 1612 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17619:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17619:1"/>
            <p>THE ARAIGNMENT of <hi>John Selman,</hi> who was executed neere Charing-Croſſe the 7. of Ianuary, 1612. for a Fellony by him committed in the Kings Chappell <hi>at White-Hall vpon Chriſtmas day laſt, in preſence</hi> of the King and diuers of the Nobility.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of John Selman holding a purse</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W.H.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Popes-head Pallace, 1612.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:17619:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17619:2"/>
            <head>A TRVE RELA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the apprehending, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining, committing, indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> arraigning, and conuicting of <hi>Iohn Selman.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He miſerable and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuous ſinnes that men are howerlydrawn into by the malitious meanes, ſubtle ſnares, inticements and allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the Diuell: are ſo many and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous, that were not our owne eies continuall witneſſes of the effect which they doe dayly worke in many, it were not poſſible wee could or ſhould beleeue that, which euery minute is throwne into our owne eares by the report of others.</p>
            <p>As for example, would or could any one bee perſwaded, that a man ſhould be ſo au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious, or irreligious, as to venture or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Houſe of God, with a preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and reſolued mind, to do a deed that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17619:3"/>any honeſt Chriſtian would tremble and quake, but to thinke vpon, in regard of the time, place, and perſons there preſent, which in briefe was this. On Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the <hi>25.</hi> of December laſt paſt, being Chriſtmas day, one <hi>Iohn Selman</hi> did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to come into the Chappell at White-Hall, with intent and purpoſe to do that which at laſt he effected, which was either to cut a purſe, or pic. a pocket: and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering long about one <hi>Leonatd Barry</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant to the Right Honourable, the Lord <hi>Harrington,</hi> was eſpied and noted by one <hi>M. Duble day,</hi> who for ſome reaſons which hereafter you ſhal heare, did not ceaſe with his eye to follow him, ſuſpecting him to be ſuch a one, as preſently after by the fact, and his own confeſſion he did approue him ſelfe to be: for <hi>Iohn Selman,</hi> after long hawking, and following of the foreſaide <hi>Leonard Barry</hi> (which was ſtill noted by the foreſaid <hi>M. Dubbleday,)</hi> the ſaid <hi>Iohn Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> after he had (as it ſeemed) purchaſed his priſe, tooke his way forth of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, which <hi>M. Dubbleday</hi> perceiuing, he came dirrctly to the foreſaid <hi>Leonard Barry,</hi> and did aske him whether he wanted any thing out of his pockets or no: to which he anſwered, no ſurely ſir I thinke I doe not. But <hi>M. Dubble-day</hi> wild him to be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17619:3"/>ſure, and thereupon <hi>Leon<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d Barry</hi> putting his hand into his pocket miſt his purſe, &amp; ſaid to M. <hi>Dubleday,</hi> Sir, I haue loſt my purſe. Then ſaid <hi>M. Dubleday,</hi> goe with me and follow that man, for ſurely he hath it, meaning the foreſaid <hi>Iohn Selman:</hi> and thereupon <hi>M. Doubleday</hi> and <hi>Leonard Barry</hi> followed <hi>Iohn Selman</hi> forth of the Chappel, and hauing ouertaken him, <hi>M. Dubbleday</hi> ſtent before <hi>Selman,</hi> and caught him faſt by both the Wriſts, willing <hi>Leonard</hi> Barry to ſearch his pockets, for there quoth <hi>M. Dubbleday</hi> ſhall you find your purſe: <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard Barry</hi> putting his hand into one of <hi>Selmans</hi> pockets, found nothing there but a knife in a ſheath: but in the other pocket he found his purſe, and opening of it, he found his money al there which he had put in in the morning. The purſe was a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble purſe of Lether into which <hi>Leonard Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> had put in twenty ſhillings into the one part of the purſe, and twenty ſhillings into the other.</p>
            <p>The ſodaine comming of <hi>M. Dubbleday</hi> vnto <hi>Leonard Barrie,</hi> together with his ſpeech to him in the Chappell, as alſo their haſty following of <hi>Selman</hi> forth of the Chappell, cauſed the by-ſtanders with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration to looke after them, and one to enquire of another, what might bee the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17619:4"/>cauſe of that ſod<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine tumult.</p>
            <p>In briefe it came to his Maieſties eare, who being then in his royall perſon, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with our gratious Queene, the thrice noble Prince, the Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> with diuers of the Nobility, his ſacred Maieſtie being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to receiue the Sacrament, was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what diſturbed with the report hereof, and therupon his moſt excellent Maieſty gaue commandement that the malefactor ſhould be detained and further examined.</p>
            <p>The celebration of the holy Sacrament being performed, which in ſhort time after <hi>Selman</hi> was brought before the Right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Sir <hi>Robert Baniſtre</hi> Clerke of the Greene-cloth for his Maieſties Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, who examining the ſaid <hi>Selman,</hi> he did confeſſe as followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:17619:4"/>
            <head>The Examination of Iohn Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>before the Right Worſhipfull</hi> Sir ROBERT BANISTRE Clerke of the Greencloth for his Maieſties Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, taken the xxv. of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. 1611.</head>
            <p>FIrſt he ſayth, that he dwelleth in <hi>Shoe</hi> Lane, and that hee hath no Trade which he betaketh himſelfe vnto. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing examined of the buſines hee had at Court, he anſwereth, that he had not any that was good, and further confeſſeth that he did in his Maieſties Chappell the ſame day take out of the pocket of one <hi>Leonard Barry</hi> ſeruant to the L. <hi>Harington,</hi> a purſe with money in it: but what ſumme hee knowes not, in regard as ſoone as he was poſſeſt of it he was apprehended, and the ſaid purſe taken from him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Selman</hi> hauing been thus examined by Sir <hi>Rober Baniſtre,</hi> he was by him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the cuſtody of certaine of the Knight Marſhals men, with commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to conuay him preſently to the priſon of the Marſhalſey.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:17619:5"/>
            <p> Now, gentle Readers, you muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that this <hi>Selman</hi> came into the Kings Chappell in very good and ſeemely appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, like vnto a Gentleman, or Citizen: <hi>viz.</hi> a faire blacke Cloake laced, and either lined thorow or faced with veluet. The reſt of his apparel in reaſonable maner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing anſwerable thereunto. Which was the cauſe that he without reſiſtance had free entrance into that holy and ſanctified place.</p>
            <p>But he had not beene long in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall ſee, ere that his gallant apparell was fetcht from him, and meaner brought vnto him, in which he came to his araignement.</p>
            <p>On Tweſday being the laſt of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>1611.</hi> maſter <hi>Richardſon</hi> (Marſhall of the marſhall ſey) hauing receiued a write or warrant to that effect, did bring vp his priſoner, the foreſaid <hi>Iohn Selman,</hi> to Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter to the Kings bench barre, there to receiue his trial before certaine of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Commiſſioners, whoſe names are as followeth.</p>
            <p>The names of his Maieſties Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners there aſſembled.
<list>
                  <item>William Lord Knollis.</item>
                  <item>Sir Thomas Vauaſor.</item>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:17619:5"/>
                  <item> 
                     <hi>Sir Francis Backon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Arthur Gorge.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Robert Baniſtre.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> and others of the Greene Cloth.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Edmond Bowier.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir Robert Leighe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>and <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Phillip Gerrard.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Court being ſet, Proclamation was made, and euery man charged to keep ſilence, while the Kings Commiſſion was reading on paine of impriſonment.</p>
            <p>The commiſſion being read, the grand inqueſt was called, who did appeare all being his Maieſties ſeruants, whoſe names are as followeth.</p>
            <p>The names of the grand inqueſt.
<list>
                  <item>William Lancaſter, Eſquire.</item>
                  <item>Edward Blackgraue, Eſquire:</item>
                  <item>Iohn Bull, Gentleman.</item>
                  <item>Edward Beake, Yeoman.</item>
                  <item>William Yates, Yeo.</item>
                  <item>Richard Langley, Yeo.</item>
                  <item>Robert Powlſton, Yeo.</item>
                  <item>Thomas Gawen, Yeo.</item>
                  <item>Anthony Barklet, Yeo.</item>
                  <item>Richard Gregory, Yeo.</item>
                  <item>George Cordall. Yeo.</item>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17619:6"/>
                  <item> Roger Terry. Yeo.</item>
                  <item>William Carter. Yeo.</item>
                  <item>Edward Kiffin. Yeo.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Browne, Yeo.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Whitlocke. Yeo.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Wonnam, Yeo.</item>
                  <item>Richard Dyar, Yeo.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Gentlemen and Yeomen being called and ſworne, Proclamation was made again, &amp; euery man charged to keepe ſilence while the charge was giuen to the great Inqueſt, on paine of impriſonment.</p>
            <p>The charge being giuen to the Grand Inqueſt by <hi>Sir Francis Bacon,</hi> the Kings Soliſter.</p>
            <p>The Bill of Inditement was preferred vnto them, for the approbation whereof, The foreſaid <hi>Leonard Barrie</hi> and <hi>Edmond Dubleday</hi> were called and ſworne to giue their true teſtimony for ſatiſfying of the Jury, and to that purpoſe, <hi>Leonard</hi> was firſt called and charged by vertue of his oath to deliuer the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth, concerning the matter in queſtion between the Kings Maieſtie and <hi>Iohn Selman</hi> the priſoner in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited, his teſtimony was as followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:17619:6"/>
            <head>The euidence of <hi>Leonard Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry giuen to the Great</hi> Inqueſt.</head>
            <p>FIrſt he ſaid, that on Chriſtmas day in the morning, being the xxv. of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember <hi>1611.</hi> he came into the Kinges Chappell at White-hall, with intent to heare the diuine ſeruice and ſermon, to ſee his Maieſties Royall Perſon, and the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the moſt holy &amp; bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and being there in the Chappell, the foreſaid <hi>M. Dubleday</hi> came vnto him, and did aske him whether hee had loſt any thing out of his pockets or no: to which he anſwered, not any thing ſurely ſir as I thinke. But <hi>M Dubleday</hi> willed me quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſearch, and to be ſure, and thereupon I thruſt my hands into my pockets, and miſt my purſe: which <hi>M. Dubleday</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, willed me to go with him, and follow that man, pointing to <hi>Selman,</hi> which wee did, and ouertaking him, ſearcht him, and with him did find my purſe, and all my money, and this is all ſaid hee, that I can ſay: and thereupon <hi>M. Dubleday</hi> was called and charged, that by vertue of his Doth, he ſhould likewiſe deliv<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the truth and the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17619:7"/>whole truth, and nothing but the truth, concerning the matter in queſtion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Kings Maieſty and <hi>Iohn Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> the priſoner indited.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The euidence of <hi>Edmond Duble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> giuen to the great Inqueſt.</head>
            <p>FIrſt he ſaid that being in the Chapell one Chriſtmaſſe day laſt, hee did eſpie there the foreſaid <hi>Selman,</hi> whom hee did much ſuſpect to bee a very looſe and lewd fellow, and that made him very ſtrickly, but couertly to watch him, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his formality in apparrell. At laſt he did perceiue <hi>Selman</hi> to take his way out of the Chappell, after he had been long about the foreſaid <hi>Leonard Barry,</hi> and thereupon hee came to the ſaid <hi>Barry,</hi> and ſpake to him as aforeſaid, and afterward with him did follow and apprehend the ſaid <hi>Selman,</hi> and found about him the purſe of the ſaid <hi>Leonard Barry,</hi> and forty ſhillings in money therein: but <hi>M. Dubleday</hi> being demaunded by the Court, what reaſon hee had to ſuſpect him more then any other man in the Chappell, to which hee anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17619:7"/>
            <p> That he hauing buſineſſe in the Terme time at Weſtminſter Hall in the Cheker Chamber, this <hi>Selman</hi> ſaid he, that is now priſoner was very neere about me, and ſo neere, as I could, and did wiſh that he had beene further off, becauſe I did aſſure my ſelfe that he had no good meaning to mee, keeping ſo neere me, and hauing no buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with me, and that was the cauſe that I did ſuſpect him.</p>
            <p>And therupon the great Inqueſt being ready to goe together, they were willed for their better ſatiſfaction to ſtay and heare the examination and confeſſion of the ſaid <hi>Iohn Selman</hi> taken before Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Baniſtre</hi> Clerke of the greene Cloth, &amp;c. Which examination together with the priſoners owne confeſſion was red vnto them as it is before ſet downe. All which when they had heard, they went not from the barre, but called for pen and inke, and to the inditement ſubſcribed <hi>Billa Vera,</hi> which with a generall and free conſent of them all was deliuered vp.</p>
            <p>That being done, maſter <hi>Richardſon</hi> Marſhall of the Marſhall ſey was called and willed to bring in his priſoner, which hee did, and hee being placed at the Barre, was commanded by the name of <hi>Iohn Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:17619:8"/>to hold vp his hand, which he did, then was the inditement read: which was this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Selman,</hi> hold vp thy hand, thou ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt heere indited by the name of <hi>Iohn Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> late of London yeoman, for that thou the twenty fifth day of December in the ninth yeere of the Raigne of our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord <hi>Iames</hi> by the grace of God King of <hi>England, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the faith, &amp;c. and of <hi>Scotland</hi> the fiue and fortie, at the houſe of our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord the King, called White Hall in the County of Midleſex within the verge, our Soueraigne Lord the King, being then in his Royall Maieſty, at White-hal aforeſaid, withforce and Arms did make an aſſault vpon one <hi>Leonard Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> and one purſe of the value of one halfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penny and forty ſhillings ready money in the ſame purſe, then and there being of the goods and money of the foreſaid <hi>Leonard Barrie,</hi> from the perſon of the ſaid <hi>Leonard Barrie,</hi> priuily and without the knowledge of the ſaid <hi>Leonard,</hi> then and there feloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly did take and carry contrary to the peace of our Soueraigne Lord the King, his Crowne, and Dignity.</p>
            <p>What ſaieſt thou <hi>Iohn Selman</hi> to this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, art thou guilty or not guilty, to which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17619:8"/>hee anſwered guilty, then after ſome ſmall reſpite or pauſe, hee was demaunded by M. <hi>Thomas Porter</hi> what hee could ſay for himſelfe, why ſentence of death according to the law ſhold not be pronounced againſt him: to which he anſwered not any thing but proſtrating himſelfe on his knees, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted himſelfe to the Kings mercy, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly praying, that after the law was execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, his body might bee deliuered to his wife to haue Chriſtian buriall, and that the goods which he had, (part of which was wel gotten, ſome otherwiſe) might not bee taken from her: to which the Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull and worthy Gentleman, Sir <hi>F. B.</hi> anſwered: Here is an Honourable Lord, and an ancient Counſellor, that vpon your true Repentance, and reuealing of thoſe of your faculty and fraternity, who are ſtill as ready to enter into the preſence Chamber of the King, as you were to enter into the Kings Chappell, which is the houſe of God, wherein hee hath promiſed alwaies to bee preſent, and therefore it may well be called the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid Sir <hi>F.</hi> if you doe this, vpon his Honours report to the Kinges Maieſty, queſtionles your requeſt will be granted.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Selman</hi> ſpeaking to the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, nominated one (who as he ſaide,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17619:9"/>was then in the Hall, which could (if hee would) do good ſeruice to the King, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealing many of that profeſſion, his name as I haue heard is <hi>I. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being done, Sir <hi>Francis <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acon,</hi> to whom at that tune it did belong, proceeded to iudgement, and asking on the priſoner, thus or to this effect, in ſome ſort hee ſpake.</p>
            <p>The firſt and greateſt ſinne that euer was committed was done in Heauen. The ſecond was done in Paradiſe, being hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon earth, and truly I cannot chuſe but place this in the third ranke, in regard it was done in the houſe of God, where he by his owne promiſe is alwaies reſident, as alſo for that the cauſe of that aſſembly was to celebrate the Feaſt of the birth of our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus. And Gods Lieutenant here on earth, being in Gods houſe there preſent, ready to receiue the holy and bleſſed Sacrament, all which being conſidered, the time, place, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons there preſent, and therefore I doe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe thee that as thou haſt ſubmitted thy ſelfe to the Kings mercy, ſo thou wilt craue pardon at Gods hands, who is more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to giue, then we to craue which if thou doſt with a true feeling of thy ſinne, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and loathing of thy ſinne, thou
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17619:9"/>ſhalt ſurely bee forgiuen at Gods hands, and being fully perſwaded thereof, I will now pronounce thy iudgement, which is:</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt bee had from hence to the place from whence thou cammeſt, and from thence bee brought to the place of Execution, which ſhall be betweene Charing Croſſe and the Court gate, and there to bee hanged by the necke till thou be dead, and ſo the Lord haue mercy vpon thy ſoule.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="scaffold_speech">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:17619:10"/>
            <head>The laſt ſpeach of <hi>Selman</hi> at the place of Execution.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am come (as you ſee) patiently to offer vp the ſweet, and deare ſacrifice of my life, a life, which I haue graceleſſely abuſed, and by the vnruly courſe thereof, made my death a ſcandall to my kindred and aquaintance: I haue conſumed fortunes gifts in rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous companies, waſted my good name in the purchaſe of goods vnlawfully gotten, and now ending my daies in too late re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, I am placed in the rancke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates, which the ruſty canker of time muſt needs turne to obliuion. I ſtand here as ſhames example, ready to bee ſpewed out of the Common wealth. I confeſſe, I haue knowne too much, performed more, but conſented to moſt: I haue bin the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corruption of many ripe witted youth, and leader of them to confuſion. Pardon me God, for that is now a burthen to my conſcience, waſh it away ſweet Creator, that I may ſpotleſſe enter into thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous kingdome. Whereupon being deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if he would diſcouer any of his frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17619:10"/>for the good of the Common wealth or not: Anſwered, that he had already left the names of diuers notorious malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in writing behind him, which hee thought ſufficient. So hee requeſted the quietnes of conſcience that his ſoule might depart without moelſtation. For (quoth he) I haue deſerued death long before this time, and deſeruedly now I ſuffer death. The offence I dye for, was high preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a fact done euen in the Kings Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties preſence, euen in the Church of God, in the time of diuine Seruice, and the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Sacred Communion, for which if forgiuenes may deſcend fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods tribunall Throne, with penitence of hart I deſire it, all which being ſpoken, he pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently left this world for auother life.</p>
            <p>But ſee the graceleſſe and vnrepenting minds of ſuch like kinde of liuers: for, one of his quality (a picke pocket, I meane) euen at his execution, grew maſter of a true mans purſe, who being preſently ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, was impriſoned, and is like the next ſeſſions to wander the long voiage after his grand Captaine, <hi>Mounſier Iohn Selman,</hi> God if it bee his bleſſed will turne their hearts, and make them all honeſt men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:17619:11"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of John Selman holding a purse</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17619:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
